Today I'll talk about advancing robot
intelligence with reinforcement
learning. And before I
zoom into robotics or reinforcement
learning, I'll take a step back and I
first contrast reinforcement learning
with imitation learning.
So one thing to note here is that I'm
going to compare imitation learning that
actually works with reinforcement
learning that actually works. That
doesn't mean that there don't exist
reinforcement learning algorithms which
don't follow this characteristics. But
these are the characteristics of the
ones that have been the most successful
at actually solving extremely hard
problems.
So for imitation learning it is widely
used for pre-training vision language
models. It's also used for video
generation, image segmentation. So the
first two are probably more popular for
image segmentation. You get an image and
it will segment out different parts of
the image.
The best models that we have today for
these are trained using some form of
imitation learning and reinforcement
learning. The places where it has
delivered the best results one is game
playing. So for example the game of go
also games in simulation. Um it has also
delivered results in reasoning for large
language models which is significantly
beyond what the imitation learning
pre-training could achieve. And the last
one is robotics which I will get into
the rest of the talk.
So the key characteristics that
successful imitation learning has used
is that it relies on of policy data. So
this data is collected or generated by
humans or collected in sources which
have nothing to do with the final policy
that you're improving. In contrast, the
reinforcement learning that has
succeeded is uh typically on policy. So
the policy that you want to improve is
the one you roll out to generate the
distribution of the data set and then
you somehow use to improve your policy.
In re in imitation learning, you take
your data set, you clean it up, you get
the good data set and then you use that
to train your model. But in
reinforcement learning, every data point
that is generated during the policy
rollout is fair game. So you can use all
of that to improve and update your
policy and that actually is one of the
things that um makes reinforcement
learning quite powerful. So you learn
from not just the positive but also the
negative data which kind of gives you
very precise um behaviors that you want.
And typically imitation learning has
given us generalist. So you have it
gives you this one single model that can
do a bunch of things. uh reinforcement
learning either gives you specialists or
it helps you specialize pre-trained
general models. So this this this this
contrast is just to give you a sense of
the difference between the two. That is
not to say that one is strictly better
than the other. So even for the game of
uh go we there were we use imitation
learning for bomb starting the
reinforcement learning self-player
search and same with language models you
use imitation learning to warmart your
whole model and then you can get
reasoning or whatever it is that you
want to um improve the performance on
top of that.
So now let's zoom into reinforcement
learning
and the first question is what has it
actually achieved like qualitatively
what behaviors has has it achieved which
uh is the only way to do those things.
So for Alph Go, it learned to Alph Go,
it's a it's a game of Go and we have a
system called Alph Go which can defeat
the best Go player in the world. And
what it has learned to do is to exceed
what humans can do by figuring out
innovative or new behaviors that humans
have not seen before.
Similarly for reasoning and LLMs, it can
go significantly beyond what you can
achieve with just imitation learning. Uh
and it can give you results just
significantly better than what you would
get otherwise. And this this the key
thing that it shows here is very
coherent and precise reasoning over very
long horizon tasks. So this is another
characteristic that we know that
reinforcement learning can give us. And
the last thing is dexterity in robotics
which I'll get to soon.
So if you look at all three of these,
there's one question that what is it?
what is common between all three of
these which lets us achieve the scale of
results we do with reinforcement
learning. So I would like to point out
two things which let um on policy
reinforcement learning shine in all
three of these domains. The first is
well specified rewards. So for alpho uh
we the reward was a very sparse one. It
was very clear if you won the game of
war. You can look at the state of the
word and you can define if you won the
game or not. Similarly for reasoning in
LLMs if we look at this uh DeepSseek
Arvin paper they say that uh we use a
rule-based reward function which is very
clear to evaluate and now since it is
rulebased you can automate it and you
can get it very cleanly and clearly at
scale and the second critical component
is can we run these policies at scale.
So what with Alph Go since we know the
rules of the games we can put that game
in simulation and now it scales
beautifully with compute. So we can just
throw compute at it. we can evaluate the
policies and we can convert that compute
to data which we will then use
reinforcement learning to improve the
model. Similarly for reasoning and LLMs
you can just roll them out um in a
cluster and you can evaluate them using
some form of an automatic reward
function making this an extremely
scalable way of uh collecting data for
reinforcement learning and also
evaluating it and then improving it. So
I would argue that these two things are
all all of these results happened 7 to 8
years uh spaced out by 7 to 8 years and
all of these successes are still have
these very two key ingredients which
lets it succeed. So now I'll get into
zoom into robotics with a focus on what
these ingredients are.
So if you zoom into robotics
um the results I'll present are from 3
four years ago and the question is what
let us succeed in robotics with the same
algorithm. So the closest approxim
approximation to getting these
ingredients is to use simulation. So if
we use simulation we can
programmatically calculate rewards
because we have full state of the world
and we can also evaluate policies in
scale because we have converted a
physical problem to a digital problem
which now just will scale with compute.
So this gets us to solving robotics in
simulation but that is not the same as
solving robotics in the real world. So
how do we uh get robotics in the real
world? By just tackling the sim to real
challenge. So how do we train policies
in simulation and then how do we move
them to the real world and that will be
the focus of this talk.
Um
before I uh get into how we solve these
sim to real problem let me convince you
first that this actually works. So I'll
start with the results real world
results of robots um in the wild. So
this is in Berkeley and the robot is so
everything is real time on board. Um,
the robot is blind and it's trying to
get over these rocks and the feet gets
stuck. It keeps trying and then figures
out that there's something and then
continues to walk.
Here it's uh it has these staircases
that it cannot see. So, it's a bit um
fumbly in these staircases, but it can
still get them and doesn't fall.
We also tried this on this grass patch.
Even if you had vision in this scenario,
you would not see the ground underneath.
So you need like a certain level of
robustness just to get through some of
these. And um here the ground is sloping
to the left. I think there's a big ditch
on the left. Still manages to not just
drift all the way and counter that. This
is a construction site in front of my
house when I was in Berkeley. And we we
were able to repeat this and it can
reliably get down this very unstable
ground. And here it's slightly muddy so
the feet get stuck once in a while but
it knows how to like correct for it by
applying more force and then just like
getting out of it.
And uh this is just walking on uh sand.
So the important point here is that all
of these results are from the exact
exact same policy. So the exact same
weights um deployed zero shot in the
real world without any tuning or
specific improvement related to any of
these terrains.
And the question is how do we get it? So
that is the focus of this work. This was
published in uh RSS in 2021.
So let's start by learning to walk in
simulation. So the idea is simple. Let's
just pretend that this simulation is the
real world and everything we can access
is fair game. So we want to train a
neural network. That's your base policy.
It will take an action in simulation.
Simulation will simulate one tick of the
real world. Um and then it will give you
the updated state of the simulation
which the policy can consume and then it
can walk.
So this would be a very narrow policy
that can walk in one scenario and maybe
we can deploy it in the real world um by
tuning some parameters of the physics.
But this is not good enough because we
actually don't want a single policy. We
want a generalist policy that can work
in all of these scenarios.
So we will randomize all of these
parameters in simulation. And the
important part is we will let the policy
have access to all of these parameters.
So now when we train this policy, it can
walk not just for any specific value of
mass or friction. It would have seen a
huge range of it and it will know how to
walk accordingly. So it's not oblivious
or blind to the environment. It's
actually aware of what it's dealing
with. And for for the purposes of this
talk, we'll call this compressed vector
extrinsics.
Uh and then the reward function we use
is to track a certain target velocity.
And then a certain other set of reward
functions which minimize work and ground
impact. We'll train this whole system
end to end with PO. Takes about a
billion samples to train it in uh this
simulation. This is RAM. And once we
have this now we we can think about how
to deploy it. But before that, let's
maybe zoom in into the reward function
that we have. So we have 10 different
reward functions. This is not very
elegant, but we tried to be as
principled as we can. So the forward and
the latter. So the first reward
functions just specify the task. So what
is the task that we're trying to solve?
And then there are a bunch of reward
functions which minimize energetics.
And then the last one is like uh
stability and minimizing hardware damage
because in simulation there's no concept
of hardware damage. So we need to inject
all of those biases uh so that it can
learn something which can actually
transfer to the real world.
So coming back to how can we deploy it?
Well, this is this vector is unknown in
the real world. And even if I estimated
that in my living room, uh it would
still um not be enough because the
moment I get to something which is not
my living room, let's say sand or mulch
or any of those, it would fail to work
and I have to retune it again. So the
key idea that we will use here is we
will estimate this online in fractions
of a second at runtime.
And the reason why we can estimate it at
all in the first place is by so the way
we will estimate the signal that will be
used to estimate it is the observation
history. So the series of commands that
are executed and the commands that were
actually issued, we will use that as our
input into the system to estimate this
online. And
the reason this signal has the right
thing that we care about is let's say
that you give a command to walk and then
one of your leg slips more than what you
expected it to. Your the discrepancy
between your signal and what you
actually commanded will tell you that
you actually slipped. This was not
intentional. You slipped forward. So the
idea is to use the history of this
signal to estimate was what what these
extrinsics are and then this discrepancy
between the actual movement and the
measured movement is what we've what
will let us estimate this online at
runtime in fractions of a second. So the
next question is how do we train this
model so that we can deploy it in the
real world and it's the idea is simple.
We'll just go back to simulation and in
simulation we have the ground truth and
we also have the history. So we will use
dagger in which you roll out the student
policy to generate the data distribution
and then you use the teacher to
supervise every single point of the uh
student policy. We will use that to
train the student model. Uh so which is
now using this history of observations
to continuously estimate what this
extrinsic Z is which will then be fed
into the base policy which is trained
with reinforcement learning and be
copied over the weights.
uh and then we can now deploy this
online. So one thing to note here is the
base policy will run at runs at 100 Hz
and the adaptation module which is the
one that estimates this extrinsics that
only runs at 10 herz and this is not by
choice it's because of whatever
computers available on board and we see
that the performance doesn't drop. So
this was not accounted for during
training. So in training we train
everything at 100 Hz in lock step. uh
and once we deploy it uh we see that we
this can only run at 10 Hz and this runs
at 100 Hz and that is good enough to get
the results that we want. So let's start
with evaluating it indoors. This is my
living room and I'll pour some oil in
it. This is this is this is a plastic
tarp. Um
I I think that is olive oil.
This this is a while ago. So this this
is the a plastic tarp on which I'll
evaluate it. And then the robot's feet
also have plastic covered on top of it.
Partially to make it challenging, but
also to protect the feet of the robot.
And it slips a bit here, but it
continues to march forward without an
issue. Can slow it down and see. This is
where it starts slipping and it seems to
maintain balance and not flip over.
Similarly, here I'm throwing a 5 kg
payload
on the robot and it seems to be doing
fine. Just just to be clear, this robot
is 12 kgs. 5 kg is roughly half the
weight of the robot. Uh I can make this
a bit slower and you see that the bot
actually goes down. If you focus on the
green dots in a few steps, it tries to
go back up and recover the regular
motion style that it is working with.
[clears throat]
Similarly here it's like the foot uh
foot hold is not even stable. So this
plank just moves with the foot. So
there's no clear estimate of the ground
that you can get. Uh and it's still
walking. All of these results are blind
by the way. There's no vision. All of
these just use propriception history.
And I evaluated it on a bunch of places
including my mattress on foam taking a
step down step up and all of these. And
it it was relatively robust in all of
these scenarios.
So let's see what happens if we switch
off this adaptation module. So what this
means is we estimate the the extrinsics
at the first time step and then we
freeze that update and then we don't
update the extrinsics for the rest of
the run. And it looks like it is 8 kg.
This is like a 12 kg robot and 8 kg is
very high and you can see the bot is
struggling a bit. So the rated payload
for this robot uh when I bought it was
around 3 kg. Uh, so I'm maxing this out
leads heats the motors much faster, but
it can still manage to walk. If you
switch off this adaptation module,
so the weight actually tilts the bot
forward and it doesn't know to correct
for it by applying more force or torque
in the front legs or get get back to a
higher clearance and just ends up
tilting forward when it doesn't have
enough uh torque to clear clear for the
next step.
Same thing with the foam. Even if even
if it is getting stuck, it um seems to
manage that fine. But here it doesn't
know to again apply more force to get
higher clearance to continue walking
because it hasn't detected that event uh
or that change.
So let's zoom into what is this
adaptation module doing exactly. So this
is the plastic surface that I showed you
before. It's flipped
and there are three plots that I have
here. So the top plot is called uh is
what is called a gate plot. So these are
the four feet of the robot and anytime a
line is solid it means that the feet is
in contact. Uh there feet sensors in the
hardware which let us plot this. The
second plot is the amount of torque
being requested in the front right knee
of the um of the robot.
And Z1 and Z2 Z5 are two values that we
have taken from the adaptation module
and we've just plotted them. I chose
these two because they show the most
variation um in the course of this run.
So if you see that the moment it slips
there's some shuffling in in the gate.
We also see a variation in um the talk
profile and we see that the adaptation
module changes its value to capture that
something has happened. Since these are
learned uh extrinsics, we cannot
interpret them very easily. But we see
that some change has happened. And after
that, it seems to have recovered to the
same gate pattern and a similar top
profile as before once the event is
detected in the bottom graph.
Similarly, for this example, um there's
a
the 5 kg payload which is dropped, which
means that at the time of impact, the
force is probably even more. And we can
do the same test. And we see that
there's again the shuffling of this
gate. And the torque is very high at the
moment when this drops. But it comes
back to a regular gate. But the torque
that it saturates to after it tries to
after it is done with adapt adapting to
this event. The torque it saturates to
is higher than before because it needs
more torque to balance the weight that
it is carrying.
Okay. So let's get into some
quantitative comparison.
The first baseline is a very simple
change over this. It's just train a
policy without the knowledge of u
changing environments. You just trained
a policy which is blind and robust to
every single thing it can potentially
encounter. This is a very common uh
technique which is used which is just
domain randomization without necessarily
caring about if we are giving this input
to the policy or not. This is one of the
baselines. Last before uh in the row
above expert is the RMA baseline. That's
the method that I just presented. Stands
for rapid motor adaptation. And if you
compare that with robust, we see that it
is a bit conservative, but it also has a
weaker success rate. And the amount of
torque it's exerting is also higher. The
amount of jerk that it experiences is
higher because it has no idea of the
environment around it. It is just trying
to be as aggressive as possible to make
sure that it does not fall.
The second baseline we have is uh for
system identification. The goal for
system identification is to estimate
things like friction and um mass and all
of these other parameters explicitly and
then use them downstream. So in this
instantiation of system identification
what we try to do is instead of trying
to predict the extrinsics which is a
compressed version of uh these
environment parameters we directly go
for these um CIS ID parameters. So we
directly try to predict friction uh and
all of these other parameters and the so
this is a hard problem to predict
exactly what the friction is because you
might not even detect the full scope of
the slip or you might not even know
exactly how much the mass is but it's
also not necessary to solve uh for the
final downstream task of working
robustly and we see the gap in
performance if we try to do explicitly
estimate uh these parameters and
interestingly it's lower than having a
robust policy which is just agnostic to
it and just learns a gate which is
robust to all of these changes to begin
with. The third baseline is um one that
tries to fine-tune at inference time. So
you take a policy from simulation and to
bridge the sim to real gap you roll out
roll it out in the real world and then
you improve the policy. This is one way
of achieving that. The RMA style is
closer to in context learning where you
take the history of everything and then
the learning happens in the feed forward
pass itself. So you'll see all of these
parameters and then you estimate how the
um network should behave uh which lets
it do it in fractions of a second
instead of trying to estimate that at
inference time by rolling out policies.
And then the last baseline is the is one
with adaptation. So if you switch off u
adaptation the performance falls we did
this quantitatively qualitatively and we
have uh numbers in the real world as
well. uh we see that the performance is
lower than just using RM. There's a
small amount of gap between what we get
from the expert and from u distilling it
into an RMA method which can actually be
deployed.
Okay. So everything that I've shown up
until now is blind
and the next thing that I'll do so if
you if you want to strive towards having
some form of a general um robot model it
needs to have perception or vision and I
will try to add vision to uh what I just
showed for walking. But we already saw
all of these results without vision. So
the first question is do we even need
vision for walking? Can we is is it a
good test bit? Do we even need vision
for walking? Can we not just do without
any vision altogether given the results
we have already seen?
And the answer is that the two scenarios
in one case vision is critical like if
you are to cross these gaps or stepping
stones or make a jump you need vision to
estimate how to make that jump and the
second argument is more of an efficiency
and elegance and longevity argument. So
if you have to collide with a staircase
every single time that you climb it,
it's not uh it's a very inelegant policy
that will and the hardware will probably
not survive for long. So for both of
these reasons, if you have a vision in
the loop, you can potentially get to
results which are much better than what
we can achieve without vision. And that
will be the um focus of this work. This
was um published in Coral 2022. So to
repeat the question u your question is
has there been follow-up work done to
use the rollouts in the real world to
improve the policy. So there are two
parts to this question. Uh the one part
is the uh sheer power of using a general
learning algorithm which is like if you
use reinforcement learning in the limit
you can learn whatever behavior it is
that you want to learn and then there is
uh this argument of if the policy makes
a mistake and figures out in a few tries
how to fix it will it remember it in the
future so the first part I think is uh
an open problem and we still don't have
a method which can continuously improve
perpetually online. The second part of
your question is a simpler problem which
is correlate which is where the simpler
answer might be to just increase the
context that you give to the policy. So
if you have a if you figure out a way to
compress the context of one day into the
policy or two days into the policy, you
can imagine the in context learning to
be sufficient to let it remember how it
fixed uh it the last time and get it
right in one shot in the future. So uh
you there are two ways to get to what
you said. One of them is more powerful
but also very slow to learn and the
other thing um lets you learn much
faster in a much simpler way.
Uh I
I it's it's not obvious if uh which one
is more complete. I can see a system
which has infinite context like what
humans have and is capable of
maintaining a memory which lets us
continuously improve in the feed forward
pass itself without needing to take
without having to take reinforcement
learning gradients. Uh there's no reason
that cannot happen but the key but then
the burden of that shifts to how do you
train this model. So you need to do
something in simulation to get that
behavior out of it.
Yes. Uh you can train directly with
phase 2 with more compute. Um I was
using a CPU based simulation with GPU
based simulation with more GPUs that is
possible. Uh most successful simtoreal
policies are actually the ones which um
don't have a history. They usually just
use the current state to deploy. And
my guess for why that is the case is
because the moment you have only the
current state that you're using to
deploy um it becomes a state indexed
policy as opposed to a state and time
indexed policy. So
if you were to have a history, you need
to make sure that the distribution you
see in your history uh and you randomize
it sufficiently enough that
when you go into the real world, there's
no exploitation that happened during
training which is preventing it from
transferring as well to the real world.
Uh sorry to repeat the question, the
question was can we just directly train
phase 2? Uh and the answer is yes, you
can with more compute. But you need to
be careful with simal because the more
information you give it in sim, which is
possible if you have a very very long
and dense history, it might learn to
exploit things of either your
environment or physics in simulation or
your reward structure. Uh and we do see
this uh if you give a periodic in if you
give a periodic push to the robot, it is
very common for the robot to just learn
to be very robust when it expects the
push. uh when it has a long enough
context or it has a notion of time but
when you randomize that as well then you
can get around it. So it is possible you
just need to be more careful with uh how
you train your policy. So the physical
parameters in this is
maybe there's a 2x compression here that
like half of what the relatives the
extrinsics are around eight. I think the
full physical parameters are maybe 17 or
18. Um in this version of vision we will
there'll be a much more aggressive
compression where it goes from like the
full image to a much smaller encoder.
The question is how for in the the
series of rewards that we have how do we
balance between all of these different
rewards? Uh [snorts]
there's no good way to do it. That is
the real answer. I think it's a very
hard problem. The practical way to do it
is to add one reward at a time and then
um try to see what is lacking in the
current set of rewards, add a new reward
and then tune only that reward relative
to every other reward. So instead of
this exponential complexity, you can
kind of reduce it somewhat to just
adding one at a time. Uh but this is
probably not the coefficients we get are
probably not the most optimal you can
get. So the question is in the in input
to the policy we use the current state
and the previous action. What if we
don't use the previous action? So
previous action has um a very important
signal to give which is what is the
command that I gave in the last time
step. This lets you be smooth consistent
and it also lets you show some amount of
correction behavior. So if this action
didn't work and you're conditioned on
that action you know that the next
action that you have to predict needs to
be higher. So the state is lossy. If you
are if you remove the previous action,
my guess is that the performance will
drop um compared to having the action as
input. The question is what happens if
you use two or three or more um time
steps of the state history? That's
related to the other question where what
if we train the full system end to end
uh directly phased to using
reinforcement learning. You can do that.
uh you just need to be a bit careful
with SIM to real transfer because now it
has more context and information to
potentially exploit uh the simulation or
your environment or your reward
structure uh in ways which might not be
desirable. The question is what uh to
just quickly explain Dagger uh it's a
very standard algorithm uh where what we
do here we we apply that the the way we
apply here is apply it here is to run
the phase 2 policy. So we initialize the
adaptation module which is random
weights. We run the phase 2 policy
collect the data. Initially it's just
going to be bad data because it's not it
hasn't learned to do anything
meaningful. And then we'll use the
teacher encoder to supervise at every
time step what should the prediction
have been. And then we will just use
supervised learning to update the
adaptation module. We will take it back
in simulation. We will roll it again. Uh
it will hopefully be better than what it
did before. uh but still not optimal and
then we will again supervise it with the
teacher module get the data set run
supervised learning and then repeat. So
switching to adding vision. So the most
common approach to add vision is to
decouple it entirely from control and
then
build an explicit map that you can then
feed into your controller to use that to
walk. And the reason this there's a
fundamental flaw in this approach which
is you first of all you're solving a
very hard problem which is building an
explicit map. So your map will always be
noisy. So if you have non-rigid objects
or if you have estimate drift in your
estimate of your pose or any of these it
will uh end up converging to very noisy
maps. So that is a phase where you have
already lost information and there is no
way you can recover that information and
then you feed that into the controller.
So since we are solving a harder
problem, we are losing information that
we in other scenarios would not have
lost if we were to directly use uh the
perception input in the policy.
So here's an example of how people add
noise to the real terrain. Maybe the
edges were enough to tell you how how to
take that step. But the moment you
convert it to a metric map and then try
to give that into the policy, now you
need to train your policy to be robust
to all of these different kinds of noise
noises which is okay for simple
scenarios but becomes very challenging
the moment you have uh you need to
precisely estimate where the gap is and
avoid stepping on that.
So what we do in this work is we ask
this question do we need terrain maps?
Uh do we need to explicitly build them?
The answer that we we hypothesize that
we don't and instead we directly couple
vision and control in the final system.
So here is what that system looks like
in deployment. Uh and I'll get to how do
we train it. So in the top right is the
depth egocentric that the bot can see.
I've taped the cameras and compute and
everything on the bots. Everything is
running on board in real time and it's
trying to
so it's trying to cross over these
stepping stones. This is my living room
and these um just got 20 stools and then
just got it to walk on it. And it's like
repeated runs with uh different levels
of gaps and variations so that you can
test that it's actually using perception
to handle all of these.
And here it's uh some hiking path where
where the stairs are uneven. And this
robot is actually quite small. So if you
give it a second here, if you see the
height of the step is almost as high as
the robot and it struggles a bit, but it
manages to climb it at the end.
Similarly for stairs, we tested it on
even, uneven stairs, up, down, all of
that across and was relatively robust.
And if you see how much it has to get
down once it is up, it is actually quite
sharp for a robot of this size. And here
the ground is extremely slippery. Um, it
just like there's barely a stable
foothold for the bot, but it keeps
trying and eventually makes it. Um again
here it's the step is very high. It
tries a few times and then it gets it.
Uh one thing uh so this is like a debris
I think around CMU and uh one thing to
note here is that it doesn't always get
everything in one shot. It sometimes
needs to try and retry and the retries
make more sense than the previous try.
That is an example of uh learning within
the context of what is fed into the
model. In this one change we uh make and
I'll get to that is so in the first
phase of training it's the same as
before with this additional terrain
height information. We don't add any
noise to it. This is perfect terrain
height that we feed into the model and
then we uh encode all of that give it to
an MLP and then train this whole system
with reinforcement learning. It is much
faster to train because you don't need
to render any perception inputs.
The recipe is the same as before. We use
PPO in simulation. This time we use
Isaac gym. And we the rewards are to
track a target velocity and then
minimize energy.
These are the different training
terrains we use. And we then get a
single policy that can walk on all of
these different terrains in simulation.
The problem is same as before. How do we
get these dots in the real world? And
most approaches try to construct a map
and feed that as input. But instead what
we try to do um is
directly integrate depth. So we render
depth in simulation and then we directly
try to supervise that with the depth
encoder that was trained in the first
phase using the same approach as dagger
where we roll out the student policy and
then we supervise it with the teacher.
[snorts] Um and same for the extrinsic
vector. So here if you try training the
second phase directly it would be an
order of magnitude slower because
rendering death depth takes a lot of
time. So you need to uh this this gives
you a significant speed up over how to
train it uh and lets you deploy it in
the real world as well very robustly
from what I just showed you.
So this is the final deployment policy.
It takes the egocentric depth from the
camera that's on the robot and the full
propriceptive history. And the one
change that we've made here is the use
of RNN. So we use RNN so they can give
you a slightly longer context. So RNN
are recurrent neural networks which can
which integrate information over time
but they're not known to preserve very
long horizon information which is why
most of the community moved to
transformers when they wanted to do very
long sequence modeling. we used RNN
which gives a good enough um context to
the model but it's we did did not ablate
using a transformer instead uh for this
task to see if that improves performance
or not.
So now when we deploy this policy uh I
to point this out again I think stairs
are designed for humans and this robot
is extremely short. So relative to the
height of the robot these stairs are
tall. So there isn't enough clearance
under the robot to just raise its leg
and then take the step. Also, when it is
going down, if it just does it in a way
which is which everyone else would, uh
the amount of tilt you would see in a
sport robot would be much smaller
because it's a much taller robot while
going down. Whereas for um a small
robot, it needs to use majority of its
leg and the discrepancy will be much
higher just because the legs are
smaller. So, what it learns is it learns
to move the leg out sideways to climb
all of these stairs. And this is
possible because we don't use any
predefined gate or foot motions or any
of that. And we let it be learned using
reinforcement learning through search.
And this footstep planning is also
emergent. So it only takes a step when
it needs to. It doesn't constantly uh
move its feet to if we had a predefined
gate of any sort. And we see that it's
actually quite smooth and seems to work
with intention and precision. And it can
handle u these kinds of scenarios very
easily
and then again uh a same policy can
control for all of these uh different
variations of environments. We don't use
any explicit maps, no explicit gates and
that is critical to get the results we
do in this scenario.
We also gave a live demo at multiple
places to um and it was quite robust in
a lot of these scenarios. In some of
these demos, I think at the bottom one,
the right foot uh padding just caught
out and started limping, but it
continued to do the full demo.
So, let's quickly compare this with
baseline. I have three key baselines.
The first is just having a blind policy.
So, the same as what we had before. The
second one uses a map and then feeds a a
slightly noisy version of the map to see
how it works. Uh it's also trained with
that noise. And then uh the last is what
I just demonstrated directly going from
depth. So we see that the gap is not
that much for simple terrains like a
slope. But the moment we get to more
challenging terrains, a map-based method
is almost as bad as blind. Because if we
sample from the same distribution that
other works have done, we see that the
sim performance goes down significantly.
So you need uh the the final action head
to know whatever it needs to from
perception directly without adding any
noise or any bottlenecks for it to work
well in this scenario.
Similarly for stairs and discrete
obstacles, we see that the performance
is better than the other two methods.
But um
the other methods still fall behind the
performance of this method. One
interesting thing is for stairs it's
better to be blind and just learn to put
your steps blindly than to use a map
which is noisy and which gives you an
inaccurate estimate of where you might
have to place your foot.
Up until now I've developed it for
locomotion. And then the same thing is
applicable also to one one uh scenario
in dextrous manipulation. So this is uh
the task of just rotating objects in
hand. It's the same policy and it's
capable of handling all of these
different variations of objects. There's
a paper towel and then there's a
badminton shuttle and all of these
things in in this
and it is capable of generalizing to
objects with very different physical
properties. So the weight variation can
be huge. It's like from 5 g to almost
200 g.
The size the coefficient of friction. So
this is an ice ball and on the right is
a kiwi which has a slightly rough
surface.
The center of mass. So on on the right
is um below the finger because of the
weight that hangs from it. And on the
left it's uh slightly above the finger
and it seems to do fine. And here the
shape is also very different. It could
be a cube or a cup and performs fine
still. And this was also trained in
simulation deployed in the real world
zeroot.
And the key idea is the same here. We
use propriceptive history to give the
model as an input and then it uses that
to figure out how to learn a general
model.
One hypothesis since we don't know
exactly what the model is doing is it
uses propriceptive history for contact
detection. So if you look at this and if
you look at the bottom joint that's what
we have plotted. So we have the actions
and then we have the joint position
which is actually achieved. And if you
look at the time when it makes the
contact or not, it turns out that the
time when it is not in contact
correlates with the bottom part of the
graph where they do overlap with each
other and the time when it does make
contact is at the top of the graph where
it's in contact and then it's not able
to achieve the desired joint position
that it is um commanding. And this is
enough signal for the network to
estimate it. And if you can estimate
contacts, uh you can figure out the the
shape and size of the object. Um that
that helps you in adapting to all of
these different variations.
Did the same gave live demos for these
as well. So in the center one, this is
an orange peel. So if you apply a
slightly larger force than necessary, it
will completely deform. And on the right
is um a an adapter. This has not been
seen in training data and simulation. We
don't simulate objects to this level of
granularity.
Okay. And again the same thing can be
applied to drone flight as well. So we
have the same policy controlling the
drone at the top and the bottom. So the
same weights which tries to estimate the
mass and arm length on all of these of
the drones. The top drone is four times
heavier than the one at the bottom. And
the arm length is also three times. um
and the same weights is able to estimate
what morphology it's operating in and
it's able to adapt and fly the drones.
It's directly controlling the motor
velocity of each of the propellers. So,
it's not abstracting away to a level
where this becomes an easy problem. And
it's also very robust. So, this is
another drone with a higher mass.
Okay. Uh it it initially it wobbles a
bit. I think it's still trying to
estimate what what drone it is flying.
And then uh we'll take a tennis ball and
shoot it at the fins. So these are the
propellers of the drone. And then we'll
shoot it at one of the propellers. And
it's still
quite robust to it.
Okay. So I have shown all of these
results and then the next natural
question is what is there left to solve?
Well, I think almost everything we still
don't have a general purpose robot model
that can control a general purpose
hardware to achieve the task that humans
can.
So, I'll focus on uh humanoids and as
the general form factor which we know
can achieve every single thing that
humans can and um show you the progress
that we have made at Tesla on this. So,
you might have seen some of these
videos. On the left is a biped walking
on hill. I've showed similar results
with a quadriped, but a biped is much
less forgiving because it's a much more
unstable system and you you need to be
more reactive. All of these results are
also trained in simulation deployed zero
shot on hardware. And then a more recent
video of the bot dancing. All realtime
onboard autonomous.
Getting the first thing to work and the
10th thing to work does not take very
long because the pipeline is very
simple. Once you get one thing to work,
you can actually pump out a lot more
results very easily.
uh and then this is uh the progress
we've made on manipulation. So this is
uh the same neural network that takes
language as input and then um can
execute whatever the language command is
here. The key ingredient is the use of
videos. We learned this from videos and
a little bit of robot data and we able
to get this. This is the progress that
we have up until now in manipulation.
Again, this is the same policy doing all
of these things conditioned on language.
And we can get decent performance on
these tasks, but they're not very
reliable. Uh this was learned using
egocentric uh videos of humans doing
things. And then we translated that
somehow to the robot results that uh
I've shown you. So these results are not
very reliable. Uh and what we where we
eventually want to get to is reliability
and dexterity to the level of what
humans have. This is this is the
eventual goal where we want to get to.
So we want consistency, dexterity,
agility and reliability in the final
system that we have.
So if we take a step back in all the
results that I presented for locomotion,
the results that we got were very agile
textures and very reliable in the real
world. And those results like I
mentioned were 3 to four years ago. So
why do we not already have some or most
of these results for manipulation in the
real world to the same level of
dexterity and reliability?
And if you go back to the two things
which got uh locomotion to work well.
One was the simulation technology was
ready. Rigid body contact was good
enough to get very robust locomotion.
But when it comes to manipulation and if
you have to chop vegetables, we need to
simulate that. We need to simulate that.
And then we need to simulate deformable
objects dough and everything in
simulation to get the sim to real
transfer to work for this. And then the
second comparison are rewards which are
much easier to specify for locomotion.
So if you programmatically write out a
reward which asks you to track a certain
velocity, it's it's complete. This is
the full task specification and now you
can just randomize the terrain and then
you can get a general policy out of it.
But that's not true for manipulation. So
for manipulation if you see depending on
if if you want to chop a vegetable and
even if you had the simulated and full
state of simulation
you would still need to come up with a
reward which measures the size of each
of the slices that are cut and so on and
that that itself will depend on what
exactly is it that you're trying to cook
eventually. So that's one reward and
let's say you put in the work to do
write that reward that only gets you one
task. It doesn't get you the full
generality of manipulation. So for
example, if you want to stretch the
dough or put flour on the dough, you
need to come up with another reward. So
it's a very manual process and even if
you get one of this right, it will not
scale to anything else.
So everything I'll present from now on
is speculative.
So let's start talking about simulation.
For some scenarios like deformable
objects, it is true that we can simulate
it except that we cannot simulate it
very fast. And then there are some other
more complex interactions that we cannot
simulate at all. But there's no obvious
fundamental reason why um we cannot
simulate more complex scenarios as we
get more compute.
So if u if we bet on compute then the
hope is as compute progresses simulation
can progress and can give you
progressively better results in the real
world as we expand the scope of what
simulation can do. And if we are to
learn from the bitter lesson, then
compute would be the right bet to take
here, which is you just hope that
simulation can improve over time. For
those of you not familiar with the
bitter lesson, it's a very short piece
uh by Rich Sutton. I highly recommend
everyone to read it. Uh I just have the
first line from it which says that
general methods that leverage compute
are ultimately the most effective and by
a large margin.
Switching to the other topic of having a
very general reward model. The most
obvious thing that comes to mind is can
we train a general large big model for
general understanding of the world and
somehow use that to define the rewards
that we want to improve our policies.
This could work but RL as we know has
exploited weaknesses in the model if
they exist. So when we do RLHF, if we
continue tuning with RLHF, we see that
the model goes uh goes completely out of
distribution from what you would like it
to do. Same with the deepseek paper,
they find that if you don't use
verifiable rewards or rule-based rewards
like they do, at some point RL can start
exploiting the rewards that you have
defined for them.
So I was optimistic about simulation.
Why am I optimistic about this general
reward model which is also also seems to
be a very hard problem to solve? The
reason I'm optimistic is because the
absolute worst case is we get humans to
label all the rewards for us and humans
are very scalable because we have
billions of them.
Um and then before I end this talk, I
would like to just revisit how we
approach the idea of robotics. So most
uh of the definition that I've used
during the course of the talk and most
work in robot learning tries to approach
robotics as achieving parity with human.
The day we achieve that, it will be a
civilization changing event.
However, that will just be the first
step in everything that we can achieve
from robotics because the actuators that
we make driven by electrical torque and
um the computers which are based on
silicon as opposed to carbon than what
we have, it is possible that they can
exploit all of that to achieve
capabilities which humans um have not
thought of or cannot figure out how to
do. So they could do things much faster,
more efficiently or better or can be
much more agile index than what humans
are. And then one system that we know
which has already done it is Alph Go
where the key was to use a sparse reward
and then lots and lots of search or
reinforcement learning to get it to
discover new behaviors which are beyond
what uh humans could think.
So this is I think a more general or a
follow-up question. And can we get
robots to not just match human
capability but exceed what humans can
do?